<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Victor Boussange</title>
    <link>https://vboussange.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://vboussange.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://vboussange.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://vboussange.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Econobiology: What can economics learn from biology?</title>
      <link>https://vboussange.github.io/project/econobiology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vboussange.github.io/project/econobiology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The fields of Evolutionary Biology and Economics have mutually exchanged ideas that lead to breakthrough for the past two centuries, starting with Darwin who got inspired from the economist Malthus for developing his theory on Evolution. Indeed, it is more and more acknowledged that companies, which are structured around market niches within which they develop competitive and mutualistic interactions, interact in similar ways as biological species. I rely on scientific machine learning to better understand how &lt;strong&gt;evolutionary processes arising in economic systems connect to those observed in biological systems&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning to solve highly dimensional non-local nonlinear PDEs</title>
      <link>https://vboussange.github.io/project/highdimpde/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vboussange.github.io/project/highdimpde/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partial_differential_equation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Partial Differential Equations&lt;/a&gt; (PDEs) are equations that arise in a variety of models in physics, engineering, finance and biology. I develop &lt;strong&gt;numerical schemes&lt;/strong&gt; based on &lt;strong&gt;machine learning techniques&lt;/strong&gt; to solve for a special class of PDEs (cf below) in high dimension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The equation below defines the class of PDEs I am interested in. These PDEs are also referred in the literature as non-local reaction diffusion equations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
\begin{aligned}
(\tfrac{\partial}{\partial t}u)(t,x)
&amp;amp;=
\int_{D} f\big(t,x,{\bf x}, u(t,x),u(t,{\bf x}), ( \nabla_x u )(t,x ),( \nabla_x u )(t,{\bf x} ) \big) \, \nu_x(d{\bf x}) \\
&amp;amp; \quad + \big\langle \mu(t,x), ( \nabla_x u )( t,x ) \big\rangle + \tfrac{ 1 }{ 2 }
\text{Trace}\big(
\sigma(t,x) [ \sigma(t,x) ]^*
( \text{Hess}_x u)( t,x )
\big).
\end{aligned}
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such PDEs permit to e.g. &lt;strong&gt;model the evolution of biological populations in a realistic manner&lt;/strong&gt;, by describing the dynamics of several &lt;em&gt;traits&lt;/em&gt; characterising individuals (for a population of birds, think of traits as the beak length, the body size, or the color of the birds).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have implemented those schemes in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vboussange/HighDimPDE.jl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;HighDimPDE.jl&lt;/a&gt;, a Julia package that should allow scientists to develop models that better capture the complexity of life. These techniques extend beyond biology and are also relevant for other fields, such as finance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out my &lt;a href=&#34;../_posts/2021-05-01-highdimpde.md&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; to read more about it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;related-papers&#34;&gt;Related papers&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boussange, V., Becker, S., Jentzen, A., Pellissier, L., &lt;em&gt;Deep learning approximations for non-local nonlinear PDEs with Neumann boundary conditions&lt;/em&gt;. In preparation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gaining a mechanistic understanding of spatial biodiversity patterns</title>
      <link>https://vboussange.github.io/project/diff-in-graphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vboussange.github.io/project/diff-in-graphs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Biodiversity results from differentiation mechanisms developing within biological populations. Such mechanisms are influenced by the properties of the landscape over which individuals interact, disperse and evolve. The documentation of high levels of species diversity in complex mountain region or riverine systems suggest that some &lt;strong&gt;peculiar landscape properties foster diversity&lt;/strong&gt;. I use mathematical models to investigate how connectivity and habitat heterogeneity foster diversity. My modeling approach complements empirical work on biodiversity by connecting documented patterns to the processes that have generated it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- only necessary when there is no featured publications --&gt;
&lt;!-- #### Related papers
- Boussange, V. &amp; Pellissier, L., _Topology and habitat assortativity drive neutral and adaptive diversification in spatial graphs_, [bioRxiv](https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.07.06.451404.abstract) (2021), 25 pages. Revision requested from Communications Biology. --&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
